<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Chemometrics &amp; Spectroscopy using R</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Chemometrics &amp; Spectroscopy using R</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Open source means everyone can see my stupid mistakes. Version control means everyone can see every stupid mistake I’ve ever made.&amp;rdquo;
&amp;ndash; Karl Broman Now I am currently a freelance R consultant with expertise in:
 Development of R packages supporting science, especially spectroscopy and chemometrics Spectroscopy (NMR, IR, UV-Vis etc) Chemometrics Exploratory Data Analysis Data Visualizations Data Management: organization, cleaning Reproducible Research: the automated writing of research reports R Training Web page creation and maintenance Familiar with R, markdown, LaTeX, html, css, JavaScript Resume  Then I retired in June 2018 from DePauw University after 32 years of teaching chemistry and biochemistry.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Contact Info</title>
      <link>/contact/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/contact/</guid>
      <description>You can reach me at hanson@depauw.edu. Occasionally I am on Twitter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOSS for Spectroscopy</title>
      <link>/2020/01/01/p1/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/01/01/p1/</guid>
      <description>For this inaugural blog post, I’m pleased to share a project I have been working on recently: FOSS4Spectroscopy is an attempt to catalog FOSS spectroscopy software. The page is designed to be updated easily with new or edited entries – see the page for details, and please contribute!
For this initial version, I searched the CRAN ecosystem via packagefinder and the Python world via PyPi.org using spectroscopy-related keywords.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Links</title>
      <link>/links/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/links/</guid>
      <description>Here are links to some of my projects:
 FOSS4Spectroscopy is a listing of free and open source (FOSS) software resources for spectroscopy. Most of the entries are packages for R and Python. ChemoSpec is an R package for exploratory data analysis of one dimensional spectroscopic data sets such as IR, NMR, and Raman spectra. ChemoSpec2D is an R package for exploratory data analysis of two dimensional NMR data sets. readJDX is an R package for reading files in the JCAMP-DX format.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bryan A. Hanson</title>
      <link>/hansonresume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/hansonresume/</guid>
      <description>Contact Bryan – Web – GitHub – Blog
Expertise in: Development of R packages supporting science, especially spectroscopy and chemometrics (10 + years). Exploratory data analysis and visualization. Reproducible research and report automation. Web page creation and maintenance. Comfortable with R, markdown, LaTeX, html, css, JavaScript.
Positions Held    Professor of Chemistry &amp;amp; Biochemistry, DePauw University     1986–2018     Education    Post-doctoral Associate, Oregon State University     1984–1986     Ph.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>